דף מ"ו Daf Mem Vav here, מ"ו עמוד ב', Mem Vav Amud
Bet, מ"ב עמוד א', Mem Bet Amud Aleph, a new פרק, Perek,
משוח מלחמה. Meshauach Milchama. Okay, so that's the next thing that is
נאמרין בלשון הקודש, ne'amarin b'Lashon HaKodesh, which is interesting because you would
think that if you're making these announcements you want everybody to understand
you, but okay. משוח מלחמה, Meshauach Milchama, בשעה שמדבר אל העם b'sha'ah
shemedabeir el ha'am when he's speaking to the people before they go
to war, בלשון הקודש היה מדבר, b'Lashon HaKodesh hayah medabeir, he was
speaking in Hebrew, שנאמר, shene'emar, והיה כקרבכם אל המלחמה v'hayah k'korovchem el
hamilchama when you draw close to the war, ונגש הכהן v'nigash hakohein
and the כהן Kohein will draw close, זה כהן משוח מלחמה, zeh
Kohein Meshauach Milchama, this is the כהן Kohein that's especially been anointed
for the purpose of war for making these announcements and leading the
people to war, ודבר אל העם v'dibeir el ha'am and he speaks
to the people בלשון הקודש b'Lashon HaKodesh in Hebrew, how we know
that means in Hebrew the גמרא Gemara will say,
ואמר אליהם v'amar aleihem and he says to them, שמע ישראל Shma
Yisrael hear Israel, אתם קרבים היום אל המלחמה atem k'revim hayom el
hamilchama you know you are drawing close to your enemy, על אויביכם
al oyveichem you're drawing close against your enemy, לא על אחיכם lo
al acheichem not against your brethren, לא יהודה על שמעון ולא שמעון
על בנימין lo Yehuda al Shimon v'lo Shimon al Binyamin not one
tribe against the next, which sometimes happened in the certainly in the
pre-kingship period there when they had those civil wars, שאם תפלו בידם
ירחמו עליכם she'im tiplu b'yadam yerachamu aleichem that were you to fall
in their hands when if you're fighting a civil war,
they're your brothers and they would have compassion on you, כמו שנאמר,
kemo shene'emar, ויקומו האנשים אשר נקראו בשמות ויחזיקו בשביה Vayakumu ha'anashim asher
nikre'u b'sheimot vayachaziku bashivya and the people arose who were named and
this was during a this was פקח בן רמליהו, Pekach ben Remalyahu,
this was actually with the you know with the when it was
יהודה Yehuda and ישראל Yisrael after the split of the kingship, okay,
so that's
a that's the ישראל Yisrael had taken captives from יהודה Yehuda and
the people said, if you take a look רש"י Rashi summarizes it
if you look at like three lines into רש"י לסוף פרק, Rashi
l'sof Perek, he says, כתיב גבי פקח בן רמליהו שנלחם עם אחז
ktiv gabi Pekach ben Remalyahu shenilcham im Achaz בדברי הימים b'Divrei Hayamim
ששבו מבני יהודה הרבה, sheshavu mibnei Yehuda harbeh,
they took a lot of captives from יהודה, Yehuda, ושם היה נביא
עודד שמו, v'sham hayah navi Oded shemo, there was a prophet עודד
Oded ויצא לפני ישראל v'yatza lifnei Yisrael ואמר להם v'amar lahem בחמת
ה' על בני יהודה נתנם בידכם, bechamat Hashem al Bnei Yehuda netanam
b'yadchem, God was angry at בני יהודה Bnei Yehuda and that's why
you were taking them captive, ותקצם בהם לאין מרפא vatikatzem bahem l'ein
marpei and you have smitten them without without you know any relief,
ועתה אתם אומרים לכבוש אותם לעבדים, v'atah atem omrim lichbosh otam la'avadim,
you want to take them as slaves? השיבו השביה, Hashivu et hashivya,
he said return the captivity. Okay, so he said might be you
know God gave God allowed you to win the war, but send
the captives back. So what does the פסוק Pasuk say? ויקומו האנשים
אשר נקראו בשמות ויחזיקו בשביה, Vayakumu ha'anashim asher nikre'u b'sheimot vayachaziku bashivya,
they took hold of the of the captives, וכל מערומיהם הלבישו מן
השלל v'chol maarumeihem hilbishu min hashalal and all those that were naked
he dressed out of the booty,
וילבישום וינעלום vailbishum vayin'alum and they put on clothes and they put
on shoes, ויאכילום וישקום vayachilum vayashkum and fed and gave them to
drink, ויסוכום vayisuchum and they anointed them, וינהלום בחמורים לכל כושל vayin'ahalun
bachamorim l'chol kosheil and they put them on donkeys for all that
were that were stumbling that all that were you know were not
able to stand for themselves, ויביאום יריחו עיר התמרים אצל אחיהם vayevi'um
Yericho ir hatmarim etzel acheihem and they brought them to יריחו Yericho
the city of palm palm trees by their brethren, וישובו שמרון v'yashuvu
Shomron and they returned to שמרון. Shomron. So that's what will happen
if you fall amongst your brothers, but you, על אויביכם אתם הולכים,
al oyveichem atem holchim, you're going against your enemies שאם תפלו בידם
אין ירחמו עליכם she'im tiplu b'yadam ein yerachamu aleichem that if they
have that if you fall in their hands they will not have
compassion. אל ירך לבבכם ואל תיראו ואל תחפזו, Al yerach vavchem v'al
tair'u v'al tachpezu, do not so on the one hand that's very
you know so that's something to be afraid of, be aware that
that's what you're getting yourselves into. Okay, but do not let your
heart be be softened, do not be afraid, do not fear, ואל
תחפזו v'al tachpezu don't tremble, אל ירך לבבכם מפני צהלת סוסים, al
yerach vavchem mipnei tzahalat susim, do not let your heart tremble be
afraid from like a braying of the horses, צחצוח חרבות tzichtzoach charavot
and the clashing of the swords, אל תיראו al tair'u do not
be afraid מפני הגפת תריסים mipnei hagafat terisim the the yeah the
clamoring of the shields, apparently I thought when it said clamoring of
the shields it meant like you know when the armies attack one
another, but the shields bang up.
It's a psychological warfare.
Right, so that's what רש"י Rashi says. Right, that's what רש"י Rashi
says, they would bang their shields together on one side to make
the other side fearful. ושפעת קלגסים, v'shafa'at kalgasim, the flowing of the
קלגסים, kalgasim, רש"י Rashi says קלגסים kalgasim means חיילות, chayyalot, I did
not get a chance to look it obviously is somewhat probably a
Greek word or something.
It's boot literally but it's used to mean
oh like the trampling of the boots or something. Oh interesting.
It sounds like something from Latin.
Okay, and what does שפעת shafa'at mean? Like the stomping or something?
I thought it meant like the flowing of blood, but that didn't
make sense.
No, no, what did he just say the word שפעת קלגסים shafa'at
kalgasim means? Noise. The noise?
What? Maybe
glittering?
Glittering? Interesting.
No, the sword no not up to the sword yet.
Maybe unless he the clashing of the shield,
and what's after clashing of the shield? He says glittering of the
sword, so they translate קלגסים kalgasim what? Hordes.
Hordes of enemy soldiers. Oh like the שפע shefa I see like
the flowing. Okay, the hordes of the soldiers. Okay. אל תחפזו מכל
קול. Al tachpezu mikol kohl. אל תחפזו מכל קרנות, Al techpazu mikol
kranot, do not be afraid from the horns, from the blasting of
the horn. אל תערצו, Al taartzu, do not tremble מפני כל צבחות
mipnei kol tzivachot from the cries, כי השם אלקיכם הולך עמכם ki
Hashem Elokeichem holech imachem השם Hashem is going with you. הם באים
בנצחונו של בשר ודם, hem ba'im benitzchono shel basar vadam, they are
coming with the victory or like the, you know, with the strength
of human beings, ואתם באים בנצחונו של מקום, ve'atem ba'im benitzchono shel
makom, and you are coming with the victory, you know, with the
strength of God. פלשתים באו בנצחונו של גלית, Plishtim ba'u benitzchono shel
Golyat, Philistines came because of the valor, the valor, you know, of
Goliath. מה היה סופו? Mah hayah sofo? What was his end? ולסוף
נפל בחרב, Ulesof nafal becherev, he fell by the sword. ונפלו עמו
בני עמון, venafelu imo bnei Amon, and his people fell by the
sword. Bo, I'm sorry, ונפלו עמו, venafelu imo, his people fell. בני
עמון באו בנצחונו של שובך, Bnei Amon ba'u benitzchono shel Shovach, the
people of Amon came with the valor of שובך. Shovach. מה היה
סופו? Mah hayah sofo? ולסוף נפל בחרב, Ulesof nafal becherev, he fell
by the sword. ונפלו עמו, venafelu imo, his nation fell. ואתם, Ve'atem,
and you, אי אתם כן, ee atem kein, you're not like this,
כי השם אלקיכם הולך עמכם, ki Hashem Elokeichem holech imachem, השם Hashem
your God is going with you, להלחם לכם, lillachem lachem, עם מחנה
ארון, im machaneh aron, you are coming with God, you are coming
with the ארון, aron, you will be victorious. So it's interesting, right,
on the one hand he makes it aware, like you know, this
is not, this is very, very serious, like what will happen if
you fail, or like if you know, if you are held captive,
but then, but then, you know, strengthens their heart not by misrepresenting
what the threat is and what the danger is, but by placing
their faith in God. Okay, so now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. מאי קאמר? Mai ka'amar? What does it mean? How do
we know that it has to be in Hebrew? הכי קאמר, Hachi
ka'amar, שנאמר shenemar ודבר, vediber, ולהלן אומר ulehalan omer משה ידבר והאלקים
יעננו בקול. Moshe yedaber veha'Elokim ya'anenu vekol. Okay, by the
עשרת הדברות. aseret hadibrot. מה להלן בלשון
הקדש אף כאן בלשון הקדש. Mah lehalan bilshon hakodesh af kan bilshon
hakodesh. All right, which is obviously there's a lot of ודברs dibber
in the תורה Torah and תוספות Tosafot discusses. Actually let's take a
look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says like
this, הכי
קאמר hachi ka'amar שנאמר shenemar ודבר. vediber. ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, למה בגין דכתיב
ודבר? lamah begin dechativ vediber? הרי קריאת שמע דכתיב בה ודברת בם,
Harei krias shema dechativ bah vedibarta bam, והיא נאמרת בכל לשון. vehi
ne'emeret bechol lashon. אלא בגין דכתיב בה אמירה, Ela begin dechativ bah
amirah, ודיבר הכהן ואמר, vediber hakohein ve'amar, and then he says, הרי
פרשת וידוי מעשר הרי כתיב בה אמירה, harei parshas viduy ma'aser harei
kativ bah amirah, והיא נאמרת בכל לשון, vehi ne'emeret bechol lashon, זה
רייט. zeh right. So אמרו רבי חגי, amru Rabi Chagai, נאמר כאן
הגשה ונאמר להלן הגשה, ne'emar kan hagashah vene'emar lehalan hagashah, ונגשו הכהנים,
venigshu hakoanim, מה הגשה שנאמר להלן בלשון הקדש אף כאן בלשון הקדש.
mah hagashah shene'emar lehalan bilshon hakodesh af kan bilshon hakodesh.
Okay,
and then the גמרא Gemara goes on. But anyway it's not so
clear how exactly we got Hebrew and if anything you would think
that this is something that you might want in translation. But anyway,
okay, moving back, maybe again, maybe to emphasize God's salvation, there's a
power to the use of the language. Back to the גמרא. Gemara.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, ונגש הכהן ודבר אל העם. venigash hakohein vediber
el ha'am. יכול כל כהן שירצה? yachol kol kohein sheyirtzeh? Any כהן
kohein can speak to the people, it doesn't say that there's only
a particular one. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar ודברו השוטרים. vedibru hashotrim. The
שוטרים shotrim speak
afterwards, right? And they say, you know, מי האיש הירא ורך הלבב
ילך וישוב לביתו mi ha'ish hayarei verach halevav yeilech veyashov leveiso etc.
מה שוטרים בממונה, mah shotrim bimemunah, the same way שוטרים shotrim are
in an appointed position, because presumably they're appointed by the שופטים, shofetim,
they're the officers of the court. אף כהן בממונה, af kohein bimemunah,
כהן kohein has to be somebody specifically appointed in that position. ואימא
כהן גדול, ve'eima kohein gadol, so maybe it's the כהן גדול. kohein
gadol. Right? So דומיא דשוטר, dumyah deshoter, similar again to an officer.
מה שוטר שיש ממונה על גביו, mah shoter sheyeish memunah al gabav,
so the שוטר shoter is somebody appointed that has somebody over him,
the שופט. shofet. אף כהן שיש ממונה על גביו, af kohein sheyeish
memunah al gabav, it has to be a כהן kohein that's been
appointed that reports to somebody. So who is that? כהן גדול נמי
האיכא מלך על גביו? kohein gadol nami ha'ika melech al gabav? How
about the king? The king is above him in the hierarchy like
we saw before, the king gives the ספר תורה Sefer Torah to
the, to the מלך melech by part, by when by הקהל. Hakhel.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, בעבודתו קאמר, ba'avodato ka'amar, in the
context of the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, there's
nobody higher than the כהן גדול. kohein gadol. So it has to
be somebody who's appointed to the task but lower than the כהן
גדול. kohein gadol. ואימא סגן? ve'eima sgan? Maybe it's the vice כהן
גדול. kohein gadol. So no, סגן לאו ממונה הוא. sgan lav memunah
hu. He's not really appointed, which doesn't mean he's not appointed, but
he's not appointed for this type of a task. So סגן sgan
really has only one function. דתניא דתני ברייתא, detanya detani brayta, אמר
רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים, amar Rabi Chanina sgan hakoanim, so רבי חנינא
Rabi Chanina who himself was the סגן הכהנים. sgan hakoanim. למה סגן
ממונה? lamah sgan memunah? Or למה אולי, lamah ulai, for what purpose
is a סגן sgan appointed? שאם יארע בו פסול בכהן גדול נכנס
ומשמש תחתיו. she'im yei'ara bo psul bekohein gadol nichnas umishamesh tachtav. That
he's there to replace the כהן גדול kohein gadol if the כהן
גדול kohein gadol dies. His job, he's the vice president. Right, he
has nothing really to do other than to be the replacement for
the כהן גדול, kohein gadol, so he does not have any other
type of a function which would, so he cannot be the, the
guy who's appointed for the purposes of war. Now תוספות Tosafot actually
raises an interesting question. תוספות Tosafot says, ואם תאמר הא דאמרינן בסנהדרין
פרק כהן גדול כשהוא מנחם אחרים כל העם עוברים זה אחר זה
והממונה ממיצעו. ve'im tomar ha de'amrinan beSanhedrin perek kohein gadol keshehu menachem
acherim kol ha'am ovrim zeh achar zeh vehamemunah mematzo. ודתניא כשהוא עומד
בשורה לנחם את אחרים סגן ומשוח מלחמה עומד בימינו. udetanya keshehu omed
beshurah lenachem es acherim sgan umishuach milchamah omed bimino.
So basically the סגן sgan plays a role in assisting the כהן
גדול. kohein gadol. He's not just waiting for the כהן גדול kohein
gadol to die, like when a כהן גדול kohein gadol is receiving
the mourners or is giving consolation, the סגן sgan is there somehow,
you know, assisting him. Okay.
And he
passes him the תורה, Torah, right?
He passes him the תורה, Torah, right? ואמר רב פפא, ve'amar Rav
Papa, שמע מינה מהמתניתין תלת שמע מינה אינו סגן. shma minah mehamatnisin
tlat shma minah eino sgan. והיינו סגן והיינו ממונה. V'hainu sgan v'hainu
memuneh. יש לומר, Yesh loma, so he has a status of being
appointed for certain things. So תוספות Tosafot says ודי ממונה היו לדברים
שמינו אחיו אחי הכהנים. v'adi memuneh hayu l'devarim she-minu achiv echev ha-kohanim.
Yes, he was appointed to certain tasks. דתנן אמר להם הממונה, Detnan
amar lahem ha-memuneh, and other people appointed tasks. אבל מן התורה אין
לו שום מינוי להשתרר יותר על אחיו הכהנים. Aval min ha-Torah ein
lo shum minui l'histarer yoter al echav ha-kohanim.
But biblically speaking, it might be that his, you know, fellow Kohanim
had him do certain jobs and he was given certain tasks, but
that was more out of like, you know, a decision, like an
internal Kohanim decision to give him that type of a role, but
it's not a biblically recognized status. ואין לו אלא כעין מינוי המרכל
והגזבר שמינוהו אחיו הכהנים. V'ein lo ela k'ein minui ha-markal v'ha-gizbar she-minuhu
echav ha-kohanim.
It's like other types of people that the Kohanim might have appointed,
you know, different types of people to take on different levels of
responsibility, but it is not a biblically recognized status. So what it's
saying is that the status of the ממונה memuneh as far as
the Torah recognizes it of the סגן, sgan, which is funny like
I don't remember seeing anywhere in the Torah that it speaks about
a status of a סגן, sgan, but whatever it says the only
biblical status there is to be ready to take over for the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So this has to be some other type
of a status. Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara. ואמר להם
שמע ישראל. V'amar lahem Shema Yisrael. מאי שנא שמע
ישראל? Mai shna Shema Yisrael? Why that language, which is obviously very
evocative language, right? Because we know about שמע ישראל. Shema Yisrael. אמר
רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi
Shimon ben Yochai, אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל אפילו לא קיימתם
אלא קריאת שמע שחרית וערבית אי אתם נמסרים בידם. amar lahem Ha-Kadosh
Baruch Hu l'Yisrael afilu lo kiyamtam ela krias shema shacharis v'arvis iy
atem nimsarim b'yadam. All you need is the זכות zechus of saying
שמע ישראל, Shema Yisrael, right, and then that I will protect you,
you will not fall in their hands.
Pretty low level.
Yeah, exactly. אל ירך לבבכם אל תיראו. Al yerach levavchem al tiru.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. פעמים מדבר עמם. Pa-amayim medaber imam.
He would speak to them twice. אחת בספר, Achas basfar, once by
the border city before they left the actual, you know, home country
itself. ואחת במלחמה, V'achas bamilchama, and once right before they actually, you
know, had the battle. בספר מה הוא אומר? Basfar mah hu omer?
What would he say at the border city? שמעו דברי מערכי מלחמה
וחזרו. Shimu divrei maarchei milchama v'chazru.
He would say, listen to what the, you know, the officers or
whatever are telling you, the שוטרים shotrim are telling you when they
tell you like who is the one who is fearful, who is
the one who married a woman, who is the one who built
a house. So listen to what they said and if you're one
of those categories, go back. Okay, במלחמה מה הוא אומר? Bamilchama mah
hu omer? What would he say when it came time for the
war? אל ירך לבבכם אל תיראו ואל תחפזו. Al yerach levavchem al
tiru v'al tachpezu. Then when they were about to actually have the
battle, he would give them this, you know, he would give them
this encouraging speech and say do not be afraid ואל תערצו. v'al
ta-artzu.
Okay, now by the way, it's quite interesting because if you look
at the Torah, the Torah has the order in the opposite order,
right? The Torah says that the כהן Kohen comes and he says,
you know, אל תיראו ואל תחפזו לפניכם. al tiru v'al tachpezu lifneichem.
And then it says וניגשו השוטרים ודיברו אל העם ויאמרו מי האיש
הירא ורך הלבב. v'nigshu hashotrim v'dibru el ha-am v'yomru mi ha-ish hayarei
v'rach halevav.
So in the Torah, first he says do not be afraid, you're
going into battle, do not be fearful, and then the שוטרים shotrim
come and say, you know, if you're in this category go home
and if you're in that category go home. The גמרא Gemara logically
reverses the order. I mean it doesn't deal with the פסוקים, psukim,
but logically you might as well tell people to go home earlier
and you might as well give them the, you know, the courage
right before they actually engage in the battle. Okay, now כנגד ארבעה.
Keneged arba-ah. Now that's four languages, אל ירך, אל תיראו, ואל תחפזו,
ואל תערצו. al yerach, al tiru, v'al tachpezu, v'al ta-artzu. כנגד ארבעה
דברים שעובדי כוכבים עושים, keneged arba-ah devarim she-ovdei kochavim osim, that correspond
to four things that they, the non-Jews, the enemies would do in
order to make them fearful. מגיפים, magifim, they would clang their shields.
ומריעים, u-mri-im, they would blow the horns. וצווחים, v'tzovchim, they would scream
out. ורומסים, v'romsim, and they would trample. Okay. Now we get to
talk about the story of גלית Golyat because that's part of the
whole message. פלישתים באו בנצחונו של גלית. Plishtim ba-u b'nitzchono shel Golyat.
It's actually quite interesting, right, just out of before we get to
it, like here obviously he's, what's it called,
when you speak ad hoc? He's extemporizing. Anyway, right, he's speaking ad
hoc. He's like not a fixed text. He's saying like don't be
afraid and then he's elaborating, he's embellishing. So is that elaboration and
embellishment, does that have to be in Hebrew? Right, I mean I
find the whole thing so fascinating of all the things that have
to be in Hebrew. This thing which its whole goal is to
like speak to the hearts of the people, if Hebrew, I mean
if their natural language is Hebrew it's one thing, but you know,
but if it's not necessarily their most natural language, it's funny that
that would be the language that you would be limited to speak
in. Would that only be the fixed text that's in the Torah
when he speaks about גלית Golyat and whatever else he decides to
say in order to give a rousing speech? Would that דווקא davka
have to be in Hebrew? It doesn't make sense to say that,
but yes, anyway.
Couldn't this be an argument that Hebrew is really what Jews are
supposed to be?
Well, yeah, clearly, I mean that obviously that was true in the
Torah, you know, that they were speaking, but the fact that you
have to have a whole discussion about whether it's נאמרים בכל לשון
ne-emarim b'chol lashon speaks to the fact that there would be a
time when it would not make the most sense to talk this
way.
Like the whole thing's anachronistic, right? Well, clearly, I mean some of
the Torah is not going to reference Goliath.
Right. Right, that's a good point too.
Slain by the sword.
Well, well that's a good point too. Okay so גלית, Golyat, that's
a good point too. גלית, Golyat, אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Rabbi Yochanan.
So now we're going to do a דרשה drasha on David and
Goliath. שעמד בגילוי פנים, she'amad b'giluy panim, the word גלית Golyat is
he stood with a brazenness, you know, חוצפאדיק chutzpadik in front of
God, לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, שנאמר ברו לכם
איש וירד אלי, shene'emar baru lachem ish v'yered elai, choose for yourself
a person and let him come down and fight against me. ואין
איש אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא, v'ein ish ela Hakadosh Baruch Hu, and
what he really meant was like I'll take on your God, okay
because איש ish means God, שנאמר השם איש מלחמה, shene'emar Hashem ish
milchama,
especially in the context of war. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, so God says in response, הריני מפילו על ידי בן
איש, hareini mapilo al yedei ben ish, ha, I'll make him fall
in the hand of a son of man like of a child,
שנאמר ודוד בן איש אפרתי, shene'emar v'David ben ish Ephrati,
so it's a playing off of איש ish and then he falls
in the hand of a בן איש. ben ish. Okay how's that?
That was a biblical idea that if you lost a war it
meant your God lost the war like כמוש. Chemosh.
Right, absolutely, good point. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי מאיר, amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Meir, בשלושה מקומות לכדו פיו לאותו רשע, bishlosha mekomot
lachdu piv l'oto rasha,
three places this wicked person, his own mouth trapped him, he said
the words that ultimately would come true. אחד ברו לכם איש וירד
אלי, echad baru lachem ish v'yered elai, choose
for yourself a man and let him come down against me, so
that's somehow suggesting that he will descend upon him like conquer him.
ואידך אם יוכל להילחם אתי והכני, v'idach im yuchal l'hilachem iti v'hikani,
what's the grammar? Anyway, if he will be able to fight against
me and smite me, so even though he said if he'll be
able to fight against me and smite me, but he did say
that he will smite me. ואידך v'idach the third, דאמר ליה לדוד
הכלב אנכי כי אתה בא אלי במקלות, d'amar lei l'David hakelav anochi
ki ata ba elai b'maklot,
that you're coming against me with sticks? But ultimately describing him in
a way in which he would be, he would be beaten like
a dog. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's true, דוד נמי
אמר ליה, David nami amar lei, David also said to him, אתה
בא אלי בחרב ובחנית ובכידון, ata ba elai b'cherev u'v'chanit u'v'kidon, you're
coming against me with the sword and the spear and so on,
so therefore David also is saying that you're coming against, you know,
you're attacking me, so why don't we say David also said something
that was about his own downfall, about David's own
downfall? No, it says no because the end of the פסוק pasuk
is, אנכי בא אליך בשם השם צבאות אלוקי מערכות ישראל, anochi ba
eleicha b'shem Hashem Tzeva'ot elokei ma'archot Yisrael, you are coming to me
with a sword and I am coming against you in the name
of God which is exactly the language that the כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, the כהן משוח מלחמה kohen mashiach milchama would be using, we're
coming in the name of God. But the point being that as
opposed to just saying like hit me, how do you point, what
you're planning on coming against me like a dog, David sort of
ended his statement by saying you think that that's, you know, your
power, but in the end I am coming with the power of
God so that was not seen as trapping himself with his own
words.
Okay, אשר חרפת, asher herafta, that you have blasphemed. ויגש הפלשתי השכם
והערב, vayigash haplishti hashkem v'ha'arev,
and the Philistine drew close arriving up early and in the morning
and in the evening. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, so we're
echoing the קריאת שמע keri'at shema we said before שמע ישראל, Shma
Yisrael, so what else is השכם והערב? hashkem v'ha'arev? כדי לבטלן מקריאת
שמע שחרית וערבית, k'dei l'vatlan mikriat shema shacharit v'arvit, he'd make these
big announcements right at time of קריאת שמע keri'at shema in order
to prevent them, it echoes the earlier point, the זכות zechut of
קריאת שמע keri'at shema saves them, right, and here he's preventing them
and it's all about again this theme about God is the power
with which we fight, okay, and that was exactly what דוד David
said, I'm coming בשם השם, b'shem Hashem, so he is countering that.
ויתייצב ארבעים יום, v'yityatzev arba'im yom, and he stood there for forty
days challenging the people. אמר רבי יוחנן כנגד ארבעים יום שניתנה בהן
תורה, amar Rabbi Yochanan kineged arba'im yom she'nitna bahen Torah, forty days
that the תורה Torah was given. Now what does that make sense?
רש״י Rashi says well since it took forty days for the תורה
Torah to be given,
that delay allowed גלית Golyat to stand against them for forty days.
So again it's very much right about the power of God and
the power of תורה, Torah, so if the תורה Torah was delayed
for
forty days in its giving, גלית Golyat had the ability to stand
against them for those forty days. ויצא איש הביניים ממחנות פלשתים, vayetze
ish habeinayim mimachnot Plishtim, and the person of ביניים beinayim came from
the camps of פלשתים. Plishtim. So how is גלית Golyat being described
as איש הביניים? ish habeinayim? מאי ביניים? mai beinayim? אמר רב שמבונה
מכל מום, amar Rav she'mevuneh mikol mum, he is constructed and built,
you know, he's perfect from any blemish.
ושמואל אמר בינוני שבאחיו, u'Shmuel amar beinoni sheb'achav, he's only like the
average amongst his brothers, you should see if you think he's big,
you should see his older brother. Okay and we're going to discuss
in a minute a פסוק pasuk that speaks about the four children.
דבי רבי שילה אמר שהוא עשוי כבניין, d'bei Rabbi Shila amar shehu
asuy k'vinyan, he's like built like a building, like he's huge and
he's solid and so on. רבי יוחנן אמר בר מאה פפי וחדא
נני. Rabbi Yochanan amar bar mei'ah papi v'chada nani. So בינוני beinoni
is basically a hundred,
I mean רש״י Rashi basically says it means he had like a
hundred fathers and one mother, so בינוני beinoni basically that his mother
slept with a hundred
men and תוספות Tosafot actually. whatever that believes that somehow if they
all sort of it all happened at the same time, you know,
then he could actually have multiple fathers
biologically.
בינוני beinoni what's the דרשה? drasha?
Is it from between many, you know, from ביניים, beinayim, from it's
ביניים. beinayim. You know from between?
Like the word papa?
I don't know. If you take a look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י
Rashi says פפי. pappi. רש״י Rashi says if you all look at
רש״י, Rashi, בר מאה פפי וחדא נאני. bar me’ah pappi vechada nani.
בן התערובת ben hata’arovet from the
mixture שבו הרבה אנשים על אמו בלילה אחד ונתעברה מאחד נמצא אחד
אביה וכולן מנאפים. shebo harbe anashim al imo belaila echad venisabra m’echad
nimtza echad aviha vechulan menaafim. One is the father and they're all
adulterers and רש״י Rashi says נאני nani is זה אב בלשון פרסי.
zeh av bilshon parsi. I don't know. נאני nana I thought was
a grandmother. Anyway פפי, pappi, that would be a papa. Anyway
פרשתורא? parshtora? I don't know what this is. בלשון אשה ביניים שיצאה
מבין אנשים הרבה. bilshon isha beinayim sheyatza mibeyn anashim harbe. I don't
know what פרשתורא parshtora is.
Anyway papa and nana are ancient words? I have no idea.
Yeah, sounds like it, but anyway. Okay. So, but
but this is what anyway but what was this? מאה me’ah right,
right, exactly. But a hundred fathers and one mother or something like
that. וגלית שמו, vegolyat shemo, his name was גלית מגת Golyat Migat.
from גת. gat. תני רב יוסף tani Rav Yosef שהכל דשים את
אמו כגת. shehakol dashim et imo kegat. Just to keep on the
previous theme. Everyone trampled, you know, had sex with his mother like,
you know, like you thresh in the גת gat in the what
the pressing for the
winepress. Trampled wine, right.
כתיב מערות וקרינן מערכות, kasiv me’aros vekari’nan ma’archos, right, which is God
of
so what's the פסוק pasuk there?
ממערות פלשתים, mime’aros Plishtim, right, from the from the caves of the
פלשתים, Plishtim, or is it מערכות פלשתים, ma’archos Plishtim, the the the
troops? שהכל הערו באמו. shehakol he’eru be’imo. It's everybody basically had sex
with his mother. The word הערו he’eru is the specific act, the
way of describing the act of intercourse.
Okay. כתיב הרפה וכתיב ערפה. kasiv harpa vekasiv arpa. So this is
the question about who his mother is. We're going to see in
a minute. It says that there were four children so there's another
later פסוק pasuk that speaks about how דוד David went to war
against and there was four separate battles with the children of הרפה
Harpa and one of them is גלית golyat מגת. migat So it
actually sounds like that these were actually I mean that's described later
in the נביא Navi but it actually sounds like that these actually
were the brothers of גלית Golyat that he fought against in different
battles and that the mother's name was הרפה. Harpa. But there's another
place where her name is called ערפה. Arpa. We know ערפה Arpa
by the way from the whole רות Rus story. Okay. So כתיב
הרפה וכתיב ערפה. kasiv harpa vekasiv arpa. רב ושמואל, Rav uShmuel, חד
אמר הרפה שמה, chad amar Harpa shemah, her name was הרפה, Harpa,
ואמאי נקרא שמה ערפה ve’ama nikra shemah Arpa שהכל עורפין אותה מאחוריה.
shehakol orfin osah me’achoreha. Everybody basically the word עורף oref is like
the back of the neck, everybody has, you know, has sex with
her from behind. So again with this whole thing about her mother,
his mother, you know, having sex with all these men. וחד אמר
ערפה שמה, vechad amar Arpa shemah, her name was ערפה, Arpa, ואמאי
נקרא שמה הרפה ve’ama nikra shemah Harpa שהכל דשים אותה כהריפות. shehakol
dashim osah ka’arifos. Everybody tramples her like הריפות harifos which is like
essentially grain that gets trampled. So once again keeping on the same
theme there. וכן הוא אומר ותקח האשה ותפרוש המסך על פני הבאר,
vechein hu omer vatikkach ha’isha vatifros hamasach pnei hab’er, the woman spread
the blanket over the pit, ותשפח עליו הריפות vatishpach aleha ha’arifos and
she scattered on it like this grain in order for the, you
know, to come and to fall into the pit. It was a
class one of those classic traps. Anyway. So different ways of describing,
you know, her mother and having sex with all these men, his
mother. ואיבעית אימא מהכא, ve’iba’is ayma mehacha, אם תכתוש את האויל במכתש
בתוך הריפות בעלי. im tichtosh es ha’evil bamachtesh besoch ha’arifos ba’ali. If
the, you know, foolish one is ground up in the sort of
in the, you know, in the mill like the like the הריפות
harifos like the like the grain is milled. So again הריפות harifos
means the milling, the trampling of grain. Okay. את ארבעה אלה ילדו
להרפה בגת, ves arba’ah eleh yuldu leHarpa beGas, these four children sons
were born to הרפה Harpa בגת. beGat. ויפלו ביד דוד וביד עבדיו,
vayiplu beyad David uvyad avadav, and they fell in the hand of
דוד David and in the hand of his servants. מאן אינהו? mani
ihu? What were the names of the four? And actually this is
actually in the פסוקים, pesukim, it names these four sons. אמר רב
חסדא: amar Rav Chisda: סף ומדון גלית וישבי בנב. Saph uMadon Golyat
veYishbi beNov. Okay, so that's actually it's funny that he had to
quote him saying it, it's actually in the פסוקים. pesukim. ויפלו ביד
דוד וביד עבדיו, vayiplu beyad David uvyad avadav, and they fell in
the hand of דוד David and his servants. דכתיב ותשק ערפה לחמותה
ורות דבקה בה. dechasiv vatishak Arpa lachamosah veRus davkah bah. So now
we're connecting this ערפה Arpa to the ערפה Arpa from the רות
Rus story which is obviously very symbolically significant cause דוד David descends
from רות Rus and ערפה’s Arpa רות’s Rus sister who does not
stay around. So now we are going to say that ultimately they
were descendants from that ערפה. Arpa. Okay, so ערפה Arpa kissed her
mother-in-law and רות Rus cleaved to her. אמר רבי יצחק *Amar Rabbi
Yitzchak* אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu* יבוא בני הנשוקה
*yavo benei haneshukah* let the children of the one who gave the
goodbye kiss, right, who abandoned her mother-in-law, come ויפלו ביד בני הדבוקה
*ve-yippelu b'yad benei ha-devukah* and let them fall in the hands of
the ones who stuck close to her mother-in-law. So it's really sad
because ערפה *Orpah* does not seem like a bad person, you know.
Okay,
so she stuck around all that time. She just did not have
the same self-sacrificing nature of רות *Ruth*, but now her children fall
in the hands of דוד *David*. Okay, דרש רבא *darash Rava* בשכר
ארבע דמעות *b'schar arba d'maot* for the reward of the four tears
שהורידה ערפה על חמותה *she-horida Orpah al chamotah* that she cried for
her mother-in-law, זכתה ויצא ממנה ארבעה גבורים *zach'tah ve-yatza mimenah arba'ah gibborim*
so she had these four, you know,
mighty children. Like you know גלית *Goliyat* was only an average of
the four children, right? So in the end they all got wiped
out in battle, but first she had them as a reward for
the crying. שנאמר ותשאנה קולן ותבכינה עוד *she-ne'emar va-tisenah kolan va-tivkenah od*.
So I presume it might be darshening ותשאנה קולן *va-tisenah kolan* and
ותבכינה *va-tivkenah* is two and עוד *od* doubles it as four. רש"י
*Rashi* says that it's crying in both eyes, so that's two and
the עוד *od* doubles it to four. Okay. כתיב חץ חניתו *ksiv
chetz chanito*, so now back to גלית *Goliyat*, it says the arrow
of his spear. וקרינן עץ חניתו *ve-karinan etz chanito*, the wood of
his spear. ואמר רבי אלעזר *va-amar Rabbi Elazar* עדיין לא הגענו לחצי
שבחו של אותו רשע *adayin lo higanu l'chatzi shevacho shel oto rasha*.
So חצי *chatzi* is like half. That all of describing how tall
he was and how mighty and his victorious, that only, that's not
even half of his praise of how, you know, mighty he was.
מכאן *mikan*, so why did it only describe half? שאסור לספר בשבחן
של רשעים *she-asur l'saper b'shivchan shel resha'im*. You're not supposed to talk
about the praise of the wicked. It's true he was very mighty
or whatever, but the תורה *Torah* did not fully describe it. Says
like, let's not go back maybe to the discussion before about flattery,
but anyway, let's not too much build up the רשעים *resha'im*. So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says ולא ליפתח ביה כלל *v'lo liftach bei
klal*. If that's true, don't discuss it at all. Why describe at
all his valor and his might? לא דמי שבקי דדמי *lo duya
shevkei d'dami*. No, because you have to describe how great it was
that דוד *David*
beat him. So you have to speak about how great גלית *Goliyat*
was, not for the sake of גלית *Goliyat*, for the sake of
דוד *David*.
Okay, so it's a little counter-balance, it's a little רחמים *rachamim* for
ערפה *Orpah*, right, it's expressed here.
Yeah, that she got these four valorous, right.
Yeah, it
was offset, the harshness is a little bit offset. Correct. Correct. Okay.
בני עמון *Bnei Ammon* באו בניצחונו של שובך *bo b'nitcheno shel Shovach*.
Okay, it came with the valor of שובך *Shovach*, which is this
whole story in ספר שמואל *Sefer Shmuel*. Okay, but where it's the
same thing is described in דברי הימים *Divrei HaYamim*, he's called שופך
*Shofach*. כתיב שובך וכתיב שופך *ksiv Shovach ve-ksiv Shofach*. רב ושמואל *Rav
ve-Shmuel*, חד אמר שופך שמו *chad amar Shofach shemo*, his name was
שופך *Shofach*, ולמה נקרא שמו שובך *ve-lamah nikra shemo Shovach*? שעשוי כשובך
*she-asui k'shovach*, he was built like a pigeon coop, like tall maybe
and very tall. וחד אמר שובך שמו *ve-chad amar Shovach shemo*, his
name was שובך *Shovach*, ולמה נקרא שמו שופך *ve-lamah nikra shemo Shofach*?
שכל הרואה אותו נשפך לפניו *she-kol ha-ro'eh oto nishpach le-fanav* would like
spill out before him, maybe like lose control of his bowels or
like melt in front of him כקיטון *k'kiton* like a pitcher. Okay.
אשפתו כקבר פתוח כולם גבורים kulam gibborim, *ashpato k'kever patuach kulam gibborim*,
his quiver is like an open grave, they are
all mighty men. So what does that mean? רב ושמואל ואמרי לה
רב אמי ורב אסי *Rav ve-Shmuel v'amri lah Rav Ami v'Rav Asi*.
חד אמר בשעה שזורקים חץ *chad amar b'sha'ah she-zorkim chetz* when they
shoot an arrow, עושים אשפה אשפה של חללים *osim ashpah ashpah shel
chalalim*. They make mounds and mounds like an אשפה *ashpah* here's like
a garbage heap, they make mounds and mounds. So this is, by
the way, I didn't give you the context, this is talking about
the armies of נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar*. Okay, so we're going and darshening פסוקים
*psukim* that deal with like enemies that fought against the Jews. Okay,
so these are the armies of נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar*. And also רש"י *Rashi*
says it's a similar like debate of רב ושמואל *Rav ve-Shmuel* darshening
שובך *Shovach* and שופך *Shofach*. So here's a debate of רב ושמואל
*Rav ve-Shmuel* about this word about אשפתו *ashpato*, which could mean quiver
but could also mean like a garbage heap. Okay, so let's take
a look. So it says like this, בשעה שזורקים חץ *b'sha'ah she-zorkim
chetz* when these armies shoot arrows, עושים אשפה אשפה של חללים *osim
ashpah ashpah shel chalalim*. They make mounds and mounds of corpses. So
that's אשפתו כקבר פתוח *ashpato k'kever patuach*, like an open grave. ושמא
תאמר שאומנים בקרב *ve-shema tomar she-umanim b'krav*, maybe you'll say oh that's
just because they're expert at battle but they're not themselves, you know,
mighty and powerful, they're just like good archers. תלמוד לומר כולם גבורים
*Talmud lomar kulam gibborim*, no, they are all valorous mighty men. וחד
אמר *ve-chad amar*, no, what does אשפתו *ashpato* mean? בשעה שעושים צרכיהם
*b'sha'ah she-osim tzorcheihem* when they have to relieve themselves, עושים אשפה אשפה
של זבל *osim ashpah ashpah shel zevel*, they make mounds and mounds
of excrement. Okay, which basically just means that they're so huge that
that's how much like food that they have to, you know, discharge.
Okay, it's funny way of praising them.
No that's not because they're just so huge, it's just because they
have like a they have a bad digestive system. Right, they've exactly
digestive issues. תלמוד לומר כולם גבורים, no no no no they're mighty
which means also I guess they have good control of their bowels.
אמר רב מרי amar rav mari שמע מינה האי מאן דנפיש זיבליה
shma mina hai man d'nafish zivlei you see from this that somebody
that's got a lot of excrement חולי מעיים הוא cholei me'ayim hu
as a general rule because we had this הוה אמינא hava amina
that maybe they have a problem with their stomachs so somebody's got
a lot of excrement they've got a stomach problem. So I don't
know why that's such a חידוש hiddush anyway. למאי נפקא מינה l'mai
nafka mina why why is this important to know? לטפוחי בנפשיה l'itpuchi
b'nafshei that the person should then take care of himself. If that's
what's happening to you go see a doctor, go daven.
Daven? What? That's what רש״י rashi says. לבקש עליו רפואות. l'vakesh alav
refuot. No I'm sorry רש״י rashi says לבקש עליו רפואות. l'vakesh alav
refuot. רש״י rashi says go go see a doctor.
Oh fine.
דאגה בלב איש ישחנה da'agah b'lev ish yashchenah I think I'm trying
to remember if it's ישחנה yashchenah I don't know because we're going
to לדרשן l'darshen both ways I don't remember the way it's originally
read in the it's written in the פסוק. pasuk. Anyway if there's
if there's worry in a heart's man he should be either ישחנה
yashchenah or ישחנה. yashchenah. Let's take a look. ואמרו רב אסי v'amru
rav asi חד אמר יסיחנה מדעתו chad amar yassichennah m'da'ato no both
are reading it יסיחנה yassichennah excuse me with a שׂ. sin. חד
אמר יסיחנה מדעתו chad amar yassichennah m'da'ato try to put it out
of your mind. How do you deal with problems? Whatever, distract yourselves,
try to put it out of your mind. וחד אמר יסיחנה לאחרים
v'chad amar yassichennah l'acherim no you have to talk to somebody. So
here you see the גמרא believes in therapy. Okay what do you
have to do if you got a problem? Don't just try to
push it down or whatever then it's going to resurface or distract
yourself from it. You need to talk about it in order to
relieve that concern
so it doesn't act up in your bowels. Okay we will end
with this.